Mary Lou Estabrook Photographs 2011.0106
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
Mary Lou Estabrook Photographs
1970-2004
2011.0106
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
57.6 Linear feet
The collection documents the photographic work of Mary Lou Estabrook in her capacity as Associate Editor and Chief Photographer of the Lakeville Journal for the period 1971-1986. Also included is photographic work made from 1986-2004 for personal use and for publication in the Lakeville Journal. Contains contact sheets, negatives, proofs and digital prints predominantly black and white with some color. Towns in Northwest Connecticut are covered including landscapes, events and activities, landmarks and architecture. Photographs documenting national and international trips are also included and may have appeared in the newspaper.
Estabrook, Mary Lou
Arrangement
Contact sheets and negatives are arranged by date and correspond with the appearance of photographs in the Lakeville Journal. The Lakeville Journal can be used as an index to the photographic material.
Separated Materials
Never dull: from Washington editor and foreign correspondent to country publisher / Robert H. Estabrook. Lanham, Md.: Hamilton Books, c2005. Dodd call number: C11189
Biography/History
Born August 14, 1920 in Chicago, Illinois, Mary Lou (Stewart) Estabrook was associate publisher and chief photographer of The Lakeville Journal from 1971 through 1986. She was the wife of Robert H. Estabrook who was the Washington Post's editorial page editor from 1953 to 1971. Mary Lou and Robert published The Lakeville Journal from 1971 to 1986. In 1990, Mary Lou was awarded a Bachelor of Fine Arts degree in photography with highest distinction from Charter Oak College in Connecticut. She was a member of the Housatonic Camera Club. Mary Lou's scenic photographs had a regular spot on the editorial page of The Lakeville Journal and her pictures throughout the paper won many prizes. She traveled with Robert on some of his trips as a foreign correspondent and her photographs accompanied his text about their travels in The Lakeville Journal. Mary Lou's photographs have also appeared in Yankee Magazine, The New York Times, Newsday, The Hartford Courant and the Waterbury Republican. Mary Lou Estabrook died May 3, 2010.
Scope and Contents
The collection documents the photographic work of Mary Lou Estabrook in her capacity as Associate Editor and Chief Photographer of the Lakeville Journal for the period 1971-1986. Also included is photographic work made from 1986-2004 for personal use and for publication in the Lakeville Journal. Contains contact sheets, negatives, proofs and digital prints predominantly black and white with some color. Towns in northwest Connecticut are covered including landscapes, events and activities, landmarks and architecture. Photographs documenting national and international trips are also included and may have appeared in the newspaper.
Access
The collection is open and available for research.
Estabrook, Robert H.; Negatives.; Newspapers.; Photographs.
- Series I: Inventory, 1970-2004
  - Photographs including contact sheets, 35mm black and white negatives, 7/15/71-12/28/73 (Box 1)
    Scope and Content Note
    Landscapes; events; architecture; people; recreation
  - Photographs including contact sheets, 35mm black and white negatives, 1/4/74-8/29/74 (Box 2)
    Landscapes; events; architecture; people; recreation; Canaan station; Sally Ellsworth Tavern
  - Photographs including contact sheets, 35mm black and white negatives, 9/5/74-5/1/75 (Box 3)
    Landscapes; events; architecture; people; recreation; Capitol Hartford; Shaker Village; West Cornwall
  - Photographs including contact sheets, 35mm black and white negatives, 5/8/75-12/30/75 (Box 4)
    Landscapes; events; architecture; people; recreation; Washington, Connecticut; Litchfield Congregational Church; Lakeville railroad station; Bear Mountain
  - Photographs including contact sheets, 35mm black and white negatives, 1/8/76-10/14/76 (Box 5)
    Landscapes; events; architecture; people; recreation; Housatonic Meadow campground
  - Photographs including contact sheets, 35mm black and white negatives, 10/21/76-4/21/77 (Box 6)
    Landsapes; events; architecture; people; recreation; cross country ski meet; storm Noah; Congregational Church; Bridgewater; Lake Waramaug; New Milford green; hikers Appalachian Trail
  - Photographs including contact sheets, 35mm black and white negatives, 4/28/77-9/29/77 (Box 7)
    Landscapes; events; architecture; people; recreation; Bridgewater Church; Miss Porters School, Farmington; Bethel green
  - Photographs including contact sheets, 35mm black and white negatives, 10/6/77-3/30/78 (Box 8)
    Landscapes; events; architecture; people; recreation; Scoville Library; Lakeville from Selleck Hill; Falls Village Bridge
  - Photographs including contact sheets, 35mm black and white negatives, 4/6/78-9/21/78 (Box 9)
    Landscapes; architecture; people; events; recreation; Canaan Railroad Station
  - Photographs including contact sheets, 35mm black and white negatives, 9/28/78-3/15/79 (Box 10)
  - Photographs including contact sheets, 35mm black and white negatives, 3/22/79-8/23/79 (Box 11)
  - Photographs including contact sheets, 35mm black and white negatives, 8/30/79-12/27/79 (Box 12)
    Landscapes; events; architecture; people; recreation; Canaan, Mount Riga
  - Photographs including contact sheets, 35mm black and white photographs, 1/3/80-6/26/80 (Box 13)
    Landscapes; architecture; people; events; recreation; maple sugaring; Norfolk; stone wall; Belgo Road; Lake Wononscopomuc
  - Photographs including contact sheets, 35mm black and white negatives, 7/3/80-12/4/80 (Box 14)
    Landscapes; architecture; people; recreation; events; Bartholomew’s Cobble; Canaan Union Station; windmill; Hartland; Sages Ravine; Taconic Range
  - Photographs including contact sheets, 35mm black and white negatives, 12/11/80-7/2/81 (Box 15)
  - Photographs including contact sheets, 35mm black and white negatives, 7/9/81-12/30/81 (Box 16)
  - Photographs including contact sheets, 35mm black and white negatives, 1/7/82-7/8/82 (Box 17)
    Landscapes; events; architecture; people; recreation; Cornwall dairy farm
  - Photographs including contact sheets, 35mm black and white negatives, 7/15/82-12/30/82 (Box 18)
    Landscapes; events; architecture; people; recreation; Gomez barn fire; Lakeville; White Hart Inn
  - Photographs including contact sheets, 35mm black and white negatives, 1/6/83-5/26/83 (Box 19)
    Landscapes; events; architecture; people; recreation; Kent Falls
  - Photographs including contact sheets, 35mm black and white negatives, 6/2/83-10/13/83 (Box 20)
    Landscapes; events; architecture; people; recreation; Masonic ceremony, Lakeville; Lime Rock track
  - Photographs including contact sheets, 35mm black and white negatives, 11/3/83-4/5/84 (Box 21)
    Landscapes; events; architecture; people; recreation; Cornwall; Sheffield covered bridge
  - Photographs including contact sheets, 35mm black and white negatives, 4/12/84-8/16/84 (Box 22)
  - Photographs including contact sheets, 35mm black and white negatives, 8/23/84-3/7/85 (Box 23)
    Landscapes; events; architecture; people; recreation; Ashley Falls; Sharon Farm
  - Photographs including contact sheets, 35mm black and white negatives, 3/14/85-6/27/85 (Box 24)
  - Photographs including contact sheets, 35mm black and white negatives, 7/3/85-12/26/85 (Box 25)
    Landscapes; events; architecture; people; recreation; Salisbury Town Hall fire
  - Photographs including contact sheets, 35mm black and white negatives, 1/2/86-6/26/86 (Box 26)
  - Photographs including contact sheets, 35mm black and white negatives, 7/3/86-12/31/86 (Box 27)
    Landscapes; events; architecture; people; recreation; Lakeville
  - Photographs including contact sheets, 35mm black and white negatives, 1/8/87-3/18/91 (Box 28)
    Landscapes; events; architecture; people; recreation; events
  - Photographs including black and white photographic prints, proofs, contact sheets, 35mm black and white negatives, and digital prints, 1980-1989 (Box 29)
    Northwest Connecticut; Bushing; santas, Christmas, Halloween; animals other; animals; power plant, Falls Village; Norman Rockwell; Salisbury Town Hall fire; Lakeville Journal; birds, chickens, turkeys, herons; Eric Sloane; Art 123; creative photography; Rands View; cows; additional photographic work for special examination; lakes, water; Tanglewood; cemetaries
  - Photographs including black and white photographic prints, proofs, contact sheets, 35mm black and white negatives, and digital prints, 1980-1989 (Box 30)
    Northwest Connecticut; flowers; leaves; fireworks; trees; churches; non-Northwest Connecticut scenes; performing arts; Goshen Fair; Institute of World Affairs; icicles; winter; museums, historic house interiors; clouds, sky; damaged buildings, cars; barns
  - Photographs including black and white photographic prints, proofs, contact sheets, 35mm black and white negatives, digital prints, 1980-1989 (Box 31)
    Northwest Connecticut; farming; people; activities; Holley Williams; rivers; bridges; horses; trains; train stations
  - Photographs including black and white photographic prints, color prints, proofs, contact sheets, 35mm black and white and color negatives, digital prints, postcards, notecards, calendars, 1980-1989 (Box 32)
    Northwest Connecticut; national and international trips; water sports; winter sports; hiking; mountains; geese and ducks; local views; Housatonic seasons; USA; Canada; England; Scotland; Wales; India; Nepal; Kashmir; Russia; Baltic; Japan; Italy; Greece
  - Photographs including contact sheets, 35mm black and white negatives, 1983-1989 (Box 33)
    National and international trips; China; Central America; Ecuador; India; Nepal; western United States; Santa Fe; South America; Kenya; Alaska
  - Photographs including contact sheets, 35mm black and white negatives, digital prints, 1991-2004 (Box 34)
    National and international trips; Costa Rica; Grand Canyon; Asia; Mexico; Central America; Cuba; Smokey Mountains; Eastern Europe; Turkey; France; Baltic States; Spain; Ireland; Egypt; Kenya
  - Lakeville Journal supplements including newspaper clippings, 1970-1999 (Box 35)
    Clippings file of Mary Lou Estabrook’s photographs appearing in the Lakeville Journal
  - Lakeville Journal Spring Tonic and Christmas Package supplements including newspapers, 1972-1978 (Box 36)
    Supplements containing Mary Lou Estabrook’s photographs
  - Lakeville Journal Spring Tonic and Christmas Package supplements including newspapers, 1978-1988 (Box 37)